Welcome back and
here is lesson or
which is where we get deep into the weeds of
Exactly. What is going on when we are training a neural network and
We started looking at this in the previous lesson
We were looking at the casted gradient descent
And so to remind you we were looking at what Arthur Samuel said
Suppose we arrange for some automatic means of testing the effectiveness of any current weight assignment or we would call it
parameter assignment in terms of actual performance and
Provide a mechanism for altering the weight assignment so as to maximize that performance
So we could make that entirely automatic and a machine so programmed would learn from its experience and that was error well
So our initial tempt attempt on the amnesty data set was not really based on on that
We didn't really have any parameters. So then
Last week we tried to figure out how we could
Parameterize it how we could create a function that had parameters
And what we thought we could do would be to have something where that say the probability of being some particular number
was expressed in terms of the pixels of that number and some weights and then we would just multiply them together and
Add them up
So we looked at
al stochastic gradient descent worked last week and the basic idea is that we start out by
initializing the parameters randomly
We use them to make a prediction using a function such as this one
We then see how good that prediction is by measuring using a loss function
We then calculate the gradient which is how much with the loss change if I changed one parameter by a little bit
We then use that to make a small step to change each of the parameters by a little bit
By multiplying the learning rate by the gradient
to get a new set of predictions and so we went round and round and round a few times until
Eventually we decided to stop and so these are the basic seven steps
That we went through and so we did that for simple quadratic equation
And we had something which looked like this and so by the end we had this nice
Curve getting closer and closer closer
So I have a little
Summary at the start of this section summarize in gradient descent that silver and I have in the notebooks in the book
Of what we just did so you can review that and make sure it makes sense to you
So now let's use this to create our M nest
Threes vs. Sevens model and
so to create a model we're going to need to create something that we can pass into a function like
Let's see where it was
Passing to a function like this one so we need
Just some pixels that are all lined up and some parameters that are all lined up and then we're going to sum them up
So our exes are
Going to be pixels and so in this case because we're just going to multiply each pixel by a parameter and add them up
the effect that they're laid out in a grid is not
important so let's
reshape those
Those grids and turn them into vectors
The way we reshape things in pi torch is by using the view method and so the view method you can pass to it
How large you want each
dimension to be and so in this case we want the
Number of columns to be equal to the total number of pixels in each picture
Which is 28 times 28 because they're 28 by 28 images. And then the number of rows will be however many rows
There are in the data and so if you just use minus one
when you call you that means
You know as many as there are in the data
So this will create something of the same with the same total number of elements that we had before so
We can grab all our threes
we can concatenate them to watch CAD with all of our sevens and
then reshape that into a
matrix where each row is one
Image with all of the rows and columns of the image all lined up in a single vector
Then we're going to need labels, so that's our X so we're going to need labels our labels will be a 1
the H of the 3s and a 0 for H of the 7s so our
Basically, we're creating is 3 model
So that's going to create a vector we actually need it to be a matrix in
In pi torch so unscrews will add an additional
unit
Dimension to wherever I've asked for so here in position one
so in other words, this is going to turn up from something which is a
vector of twelve thousand three hundred and ninety six long
Into a matrix with twelve thousand three hundred ninety-six rows and one column
That's just what pi torch expects to see
So now we're going to turn our X&Y into a data set and a data set is a very specific
Concept in pi torch. It's something which we can index into using square brackets
And when we do so it's expected to return a double
So here if we look at
How we're going to create this data set
and when we index into it, it's going to return a tuple containing our
independent variable and a dependent variable
For each
particular row and
so to do that we can use the Python zip function which takes one element of the first thing and
Combines it with concatenates it with one element of the second thing and then it does that again and again and again and
so then if we create a list of those it gives us a
It is as a data set. It gives us a list which when we index into it, it's going to contain one image and
one label and so here you can see why there's my label and my image I won't print out the whole thing, but it's a
784 long vector
So that's a really important concept a data set is something that you can index into and get back at Apple
And Here I am this is called destructuring the tupple
which means I'm taking the two parts of the tupple and
Putting the first part in one variable in the second part in the other variable, which is something we do a lot in Python
It's pretty handy a lot of other languages support that as well
Repeat the same three steps for a validation set. So we've now got a training data set and a validation data set
Right, so now we need to
initialize our parameters and
So to do that as we've discussed we just do it randomly. So here's a function. They're given some
size
Some some shape if you like
we'll
randomly initialize
Using a normal random number distribution in pi torch that's what Rand in does and we can hit shift tab to see
That works, okay
And it says here that it's going to have a variance of one
So I probably shouldn't call this standard deviation
I probably should call this variance actually
so multiply it by the variance - to change its variance to whatever is requested which will default to one and
then as we talked about when it comes to
Calculating our gradients we have to tell PI torch
Which things we want gradients for and the way we do that is requires gred underscore
Remember this underscore at the end is a special magic symbol which tells python
Tells play torch that we want this function to actually change the thing that it's referring to so this will change
this
Tensor
Such that it requires radiance
So here's some weights so our weights
are going to need to be
28 by 28 by one shape 28 by 28 because every pixel is going to need a weight and
Then one because we're going to need again. We're going to need to have that that that unit
Access to make it into a column
So that's what piped watch expects
So there's our weights
Now just weights by pixels actually isn't going to be enough because weights by pixels were always equals zero
When the pixels are equal to zero, it has a zero intercept
So we really want something where it's like W X plus B a line. So the B is we call the bias and
So that's just going to be a single number. So let's grab a single number for our bias
so
Remember I told you there's a difference between the parameters and weights. So actually speaking so here the weights are
the W in this equation
the bias is B in this equation and the whites and bias together is
The parameters of the function they're all the things that we're going to change
They're all the things that have gradients that we're going to update
So there's an important bit of jargon for you the weights and biases of the model are the parameters
We can yes question
What's the difference between gradient descent and stochastic gradient descent
So far we've only done gradient descent will be doing stochastic gradient descent in a few minutes
We can now create a calculated prediction for one image so we can take an image such as the first one and
multiply by the weights only to transpose them to make them line up in terms of the rows and columns and add it up and
add the bias and there is a
prediction
We want to do that for every image we could do that with a for loop and that would be really really slow
it wouldn't run on the GPU and it wouldn't run in optimize and see code so we actually want to use
Always to do kind of like looping over pixels looping over images
You always need to try to make sure you're doing that without a Python or loop
in this case
Doing this calculation for lots of rows and columns is a mathematical
operation called matrix multiply
so if you've
Forgotten your matrix multiplication or maybe never quite got around to it at a high school
It would be a good idea to he'll look at Khan Academy or something to learn
About what it is, but it's actually I'll give you the quick answer. This is from Wikipedia if these are two matrices a and B
then this element here 1 comma 2 in the output is going to be equal to
The first bit here times the first bit here plus the second bit here times the second bit here
So it's going to be a 1 2 times a 1 1
Plus B 2 2 times a 1 2 that's you can see the orange matches the orange
Ditto for over here
this would be equal to b1 3 times a 3 1 plus B 2 3 times a 3 2 and so forth for every
Here's a great picture of that in action
If you look at matrix
multiplication X Y Z another way to think of it is we can kind of flip the second bit over on top and then
Multiply each bit together and add them up
multiplied each bit together and add them up and you can see always the second one here and ends up in the second spot and
The first one ends up in the first bud
And that's what matrix multiplication is
so we can do our
Up by using matrix multiplication and in
Python and therefore pay torch matrix multiplication is the @ sign operator
So when you see that, that means matrix multiply
so here is our
20.2 336 if I do a matrix multiply of
Our
Training set by our weights and then we add the bias and
Here is our twenty point three three six for the first one and you can see though. It's doing every single
One, okay. So that's really important is the matrix model location gives us an optimized way to do these
Simple linear functions, whereas many kind of rows and columns as we want
So this is one of the two fundamental equations of any neural network
Some rows of data rows and columns of data much use multiplied
Some ways add some bias and the second one which was here in a moment is an activation function
So that is some predictions from our randomly initialized model so we can check how good our
Model is and so to do that we can decide that
Anything greater than zero?
We will call a three and anything less than zero we will call a seven so Preds
Greater than zero tells us whether or not something is predicted to be a tree or not
Then turn that into a float
so rather than true and false make it one in zero because it's what our training set contains and then
check with our our
our
thresholded predictions
Are equal to our training set and this will return true
Every time a row is correctly predicted and false. Otherwise
So if we take all those trues and falses and turn them into floats, so that'll be ones and zeroes and then take their mean
It's point four nine so not surprisingly our randomly initialized model is right about half the time at predicting three years from sevens I
Added one more method here, which is dot item
without item
This would return a tensor
It's a rank zero tensor. It has no rows. It has no columns
it just it's just a number on its own, but I actually wanted to
Unwrap it to create a normal Python scaler mainly just because I wanted to see them easily see the full
Set of decimal places and the reason for that is I want to show you how we're going to calculate the derivative on the accuracy
By changing a parameter a tiny bit
so let's take one parameter which will be weights zero and
Multiply it by one point zero one
and so that's going to make it a little bit bigger and
then if I calculate how the
The accuracy changes based on the change in that weight that will be the gradient of
The accuracy with respect to that parameter so I can do that by calculating
my new set of predictions and then I can threshold them and then I can check whether they're equal to the training set and
Then take the mean
And I get back
Exactly the same number
so remember that
Gradient is
equal to
Rise over run if you remember back to your calculus or if you'd forgotten your calculus. Hopefully you've reviewed it on Khan Academy
so
The change in the Y so why new - why old which is
0.49 1 2 etc minus 0.49 1 2 etc, which is 0
This change
will give us 0 so at this point we have a problem our derivative is
Zero so we have zero gradients
Which means our step will be zero which means our prediction will be unchanged
Okay
so we have a problem and our problem is that our gradient is zero and with a gradient of
Zero we can't take a step and we can't get better predictions. And so
Intuitively speaking
the reason that our gradient is zero is because when we change a single pixel by a tiny bit
we might not ever in any way change an actual prediction to change from a three predicting a three to a seven or
Vice versa because we have this we have this threshold
And so in other words our
Our accuracy
Loss function here is very bumpy. It's like flat step flat step flat step. So it's got this
this
Zero gradient all over the place. So what we need to do is use something other than
accuracy as
our loss function
So, let's try and create a new function and what this new function is going to do is it's going to
Give us a better value
Kind of in in much the same way that
Accuracy gives a better value. So this is the loss member of small losses better
so to give us a lower loss when the accuracy is better, but it won't have a
zero
gradient
A slightly better prediction needs to have a slightly better loss
So, let's have a look an example
let's say our
Targets our labels of like that there is three. Oh
There's just three rows three images here one zero one, okay
And we've made some predictions from a neural net and those predictions gave us point. Nine point four point two
so now consider
This loss function a loss function. We're going to use torch dot where which is basically the same as
This list comprehension is basically an if statement so it's going to say for for where target equals one
We're going to return 1 minus predictions. So here target is one so it'll be 1 minus 0.9 and
Where target is not 1 it'll just be predictions
so well these
Examples here. The first one target equals 1
will be 1
minus 0.9 0.1
The next one is target equals 0 so to piss people the prediction just 0.4
And then for the third one, it's a 1/4 target
So it'll be 1 minus prediction, which is 0.8. And so you can see here when the
Prediction is correct. Correct. In other words, it's a number, you know
It's a high number when the target is 1 and a low number when the target is 0
These numbers are going to be smaller. So the worst one is when we predicted
0.2. So we're pretty we really thought that was actually a zero
But it's actually a 1 so we ended up with a 0.8 here because this is 1 minus prediction
1 minus 0.2
0.8
So we can then take the mean of all of these to calculate a loss
So if you think about it this loss
will be the smallest if
The predictions are exactly right. So if we did
Frictions
Is actually identical to the targets
We'll be
Zero zero zero
okay, where else if they were exactly wrong though say they were
one -
And it's 1 1 1
So it's going to be the loss will be better ie smaller when the predictions are closer to the targets
And so here we can now take the mean and when we do we get here point four three three
Let's say we change
This last bad one in accurate prediction from zero point two
to zero
point eight and
The loss gets better from point four three to 0.23 but this is just this function is torched. We're not mean
So this is actually pretty good. This is actually a loss function which pretty closely tracks accuracy was the accuracies better
The loss will be smaller
But also it doesn't have these zero gradients because every time we change the prediction the loss changes
Because the prediction is literally harder the loss that's pretty neat, isn't it?
One problem is this is only going to work. Well, as long as the predictions are between 0 & 1
Otherwise, this one - prediction thing is going to look a bit funny
We should try and find a way to ensure that the predictions are always between
zero and one and that's also going to just make a lot more intuitive sense because you know
we like to be able to kind of think of these as if they're like
probabilities or at least nicely scaled numbers
so we need some function that can take our
numbers
Have a look
Ex-something which can take these big numbers and turn them all into numbers between zero and one and it so happens that we have
Exactly the right function. It's called
the sigmoid function
so the sigmoid function looks like this if
You pass in a really small number you get a number very close to zero
If you pass in a big number you get a number very close to 1
it never gets past one and
It never goes smaller than zero and then it's kind of like this smooth curve between and in the middle
It looks a lot like the y equals x line
This is the definition of the sigmoid function
It's 1 over 1 plus e to the minus X
What is X X is just e to the power of
something
so if we look at e
It's just a number like pi this is so simple, it's just a number that has a particular value right? So if we go a
Squared and we look at
It's going to be a tensor here's PI torch
It could have float
There we go and you can see that these are the same number so that's what torch dot X means
Okay, so you know for me when I see these kinds of interesting functions, I don't worry too much about
The definition what I care about is the shape
alright
So you can have a play around with graphing calculators or whatever to kind of see
Why it is that you end up with this shape from this particular equation
but for me, I just never think about that it never
Really matters to me what's important is this sigmoid shape, which is what we want. It's something that squashes
every number to be between naught and 1
So we can change em nest loss to be exactly the same as it was before but first we can make everything into sigmoid
First and then use torch don't wear so that is a loss function that has all the properties we want. It's
At something which is going to be have not have any of those nasty
Zero gradients and we've ensured that the input to the wear
Is between Norton one
So
The reason we did this is because our our accuracy
Was
Kind of what we really care about is a good accuracy. We can't use it to get our gradients. Just just to create our step
to improve our parameters
So we can change
Our our accuracy to another function that is similar in terms of it
It's better when the accuracy is better, but it also does not have these zero gradients
And so you can see now where why we have a metric and a loss
the metric is the thing we actually care about the loss is the thing that's similar to what we care about but has a
nicely behaved
gradient
Sometimes the thing you care about your metric does have a nicely defined gradient and you can use it directly as a loss
For example, we often use means grade error
but for classification
unfortunately not
So we need to now use this to
To update the parameters
And so there's a couple of ways we could do this one would be to loop through every image
Calculate a prediction for that image
and then
calculate a loss and then do a step and
Then step the other parameters and then do that again for the next image in the next image in the next image
That's going to be really slow
Because we're we're doing a single step for a single image
So that would mean an epoch would take quite a while. We could go much faster
By doing every single image in the data set
so a big matrix multiplication
It can all be paralyzed on the GPU and then so then we can
We could then do a step based on the gradients looking at the entire
Notice it
But now that's going to be like a lot of work
to just update the weights once remember sometimes our datasets have
Millions or tens of millions of items. So that's probably a bad idea
too
So why not compromise? Let's grab a few data items at a time
To calculate our loss and our step
now if we grab a few data items at a time those two data items are called a mini ditch and
a mini batch just means a
few pieces of data
And so the size of your mini batch is called not surprisingly the batch size, right?
so the bigger the batch size the closer you get to the full size of your data set the longer it's going to take to
Calculate a single
Set of losses a single step
But the the more accurate it's going to be it's going to be like the gradients are going to be
much closer to the true data set gradients and
then the smaller the batch size the faster each step we'll be able to do but those steps will represent a
Smaller number of items and so they won't be such an accurate
approximation of the real gradient of the whole data set
Is there a reason the mean of the loss is calculated over say doing a median and
The median is less prone to getting influenced by outliers
The example you gave if the third point which was wrongly predicted as an outlier
Then the derivative would push the function away while doing SGD and a median could be better in that case
Honestly, I've never tried using a median
The problem with a median is it ends up really only caring about one number which is the number in the middle?
So it could end up
really pretty much ignoring
All of the things at each end and that all it really cares about is the order of things
So my guess is that you would end up with something that is only good at predicting
one thing in the middle
But I haven't tried it be interesting to see
well, I guess the other thing that would happen with a median is you would have a lot of zero gradients I think because it's
Picking the thing in the middle and you could you know change
Your values and the thing in the middle
Might well wouldn't be zero gradients, but bumpy gradients. I think in the middle would suddenly jump to being a different item
So it might not behave very well. That's that's my guess. You should try it
Okay, so how do we
Ask for a few items at a time
It turns out that pi torch and faster. I provide something to do that for you you can pass in
any data set to this class core data loader and
It will grab a few items from that data set at a time. You can ask for how many by asking for a batch size
And then you can yeah
Well, as you can see, it will grab a few items at a time until it's grabbed all of them
So here I'm saying let's create a collection that just contains all the numbers from nought to 14
Let's pass that into a data loader with a batch size of five
And then that's going to be something it's called an iterator in Python
It's something that you can ask for one more thing from an iterator if you pass an iterator to list in Python
It returns all of the things from the iterator. So here are my three
Mini batches and you'll see here all the numbers from naught to 15 appear
They appear in a random order and they appear five at a time. They appear in random order because shuffle equals true, so
Normally in the training set we ask for things to be shuffled
So it gives us a little bit more randomization more randomization is it's good
Because it makes it harder for it to kind of learn what the data set looks like
So that's what a data loader weather that's how our date loader is created
Now
Remember though that our data sets actually return
Tuples and here I've just got single intz so let's actually create a tuple
So if we enumerate all the letters of English, then that means that returns
Zero A 1 B 2 C cetera. Let's make that our data set. So if we pass that
To a data loader with a batch size of 6 and as you can see it returns
tuples
containing
6 of the first things and the associated six of the second things. So this is like our
independent variable and this is like our
Dependent variable. Okay, and so and then at the end, you know that with the batch size weren't necessarily exactly
Divided nicely into the full size of the data set you might end up with a smaller
batch
So basically then we already have a data set remember
and so we could pass it to a data loader and then we can basically say this an
Iterator in Python is something that you can actually loop through
So when we say for in data loader, it's going to return a tuple
we can D structure it into the first bit and the second bit and
So that's going to be our x and y we can calculate our predictions
we can calculate our loss from the predictions and the targets we can ask it to calculate our gradients and
Then we can update our parameters just like we did in our toy SGD example for the quadratic equation
so that's reinitialize our weights and bias with the same two lines of code before let's create the data loader this time from our
Actual M. Nest data set and create a nice big batch size
So we do plenty of work each time and just to take a look
Let's just grab the first thing from the data loader first is a fast AI function which just grabs the first thing from an iterator
It's just useful to look at you know, we're kind of an arbitrary mini batch
So here is the shape we're going to have the first mini batch is
256 rows of 784 long that's 28 by 28. So 256 flattened out images and
Labels that are 1 1 because there's just the number 0 or the number 1 depending on whether as a 3 or a 7
Who the same for the validation set so here's a validation data loader
And so let's grab a
Batch here testing pass it into well, why do we do that? We should
What look
Yeah, I guess yeah
Actually for our testing, I'm going to just manually grab the first four things just so that we can make sure everything lines up
So so let's grab just the first four things. We'll call that a batch
Pass it into that linear function. We created earlier or remember linear
Was just ex patch at weights matrix model play + bias
And
So that's going to give us four results. That's a prediction or each of those four images and
So then we can calculate the loss using that loss function. We just used and let's just grab the first four
Items of the training set and there's the loss
Okay, and so now we can calculate the gradients and so the gradients are
784 by one
so in other words
it's a column where every
weight as a gradient is its what's the change in loss for a small change in that parameter and
Then the bias has a gradient. That's a single number because the bias is just a single number
We can take those three steps and put it in a function
So if you pass if you this is calculate gradient
You pass it an X batch or Y batch and some model then it's going to calculate the predictions
calculate the loss and do the backward step and
Here we see calculate gradient and so we can get there
just to take a look the mean of the weights gradient and the bias gradient and
There it is
A second time and look notice. I have not done any
Step here. This is exactly the same parameters. I get a different value
To concern you would expect to get the same gradient every time you called it with the same data
Why if the gradients changed?
That's because los dot backward does not just calculate the gradients
It calculates the gradients and adds them to the existing gradients the things in the dot grad
attribute
The reasons for that we'll come to later but that's a now the thing to know is just it does that
So actually what we need to do is to call
grad, zero underscore so dot zero returns a tensor containing zeros and
Remember underscore does it in place so that updates?
The weights grad attribute, which is a tensor to contain zeros
So now if I do that and call it again, I will get exactly the same number
so here is
how you
Train one epoch with SGD loop through the data loader grabbing the X patch in the Y batch
Calculate the gradient
prediction loss backward
Each other parameters we're going to be passing those in so there's going to be the
768 weights and the one bias and then for each of those
Update the parameter
To go - equals gradient times learning rate. That's our
Gradient descent step and then zero it out for the next time around the loop
I'm not just saying P minus equals I'm saying P
Data- equals and the reason for that. Is that remember
PI torch keeps track of all of the calculations we do so that it can calculate the gradient
well, I don't want to calculating the gradient of my
Gradient descent step. That's like not part of the model, right?
So dot data is a special attribute in pi touch where if you write to it, it tells play torch not to
Update the gradients using that calculation. So this is your most basic
standard
SGD stochastic gradient descent loop so now we can answer that earlier question the difference between stochastic gradient descent and
Gradient descent is that gradient descent does not have this
That loops through each
mini-batch for gradient descent it does it on the whole data set each time around so train epoch or
Gradient descent would simply not have the ball loop at all
but instead it would calculate the gradient for the whole data set and
Update the parameters based on the whole data set which we never really do in practice. We always use
mini vetches for various sizes
Okay, so we can take the
Function we had before where we compare the predictions to
Whether that well that we used to be comparing the predictions to whether they were greater or less than zero, right?
But now that we're doing the sigmoid remember the sigmoid will squish everything between Norton one
So now we should compare the predictions to whether they're greater than 0.5 or not if they're greater than 0.5
Just to look back at our sigmoid function
So zero, what used to be zero is now on the sigmoid is 0.5
Okay, so we need to just to make that slight change to our measure of accuracy
So to calculate the accuracy for some X batch and some Y batch oh this is actually assumed this is actually the predictions
Then we take the sigmoid of the predictions. We compare them to 0.5 to tell us whether it's a 3 or not
we check what the actual target was to see which ones are correct and
Then we take the mean of those
after converting the boolean stir floats
So we can check that accuracy. Let's take our batch put it through our simple linear model
Compare it to the four items of the training set and there's the accuracy
So if we do that for every batch in the validation set then we can loop through with a list comprehension
every batch in the validation set
Accuracy based on some model
stack those all up together so that this is a list right if we want to turn that list into a tensor where the
Items of the list of the tensor are the items of the list. That's what stack does
So we can stack up all those
Take the mean
Convert it to a standard Python scalar. We're calling that item
round it to four decimal places just for display and so here is our
Validation set accuracy as you would expect it's about 50% because it's random
So we can now train for one epoch so
we can say
remember train epoch
needed
The parameters so our parameters in this case are the weights tensor and the bias tensor
One epoch using the linear one model with the learner with a learning rate of one with these two parameters and
Then validate and order that
Accuracy is now
68.8% So we've we've trained an epoch
So let's just repeat that
many times
Brain invalidate and you can see the accuracy goes up and up and up and up and up to about 97%
So
Scroll we've built an
SGD optimizer of a simple linear function that
Is getting about 97 percent on our simplified m nest where there's just the threes in the sevens
So a lot of steps there, let's simplify this through some refactoring
So the kind of simple refactoring we're going to do
We're going to do a couple but the basic idea is we're going to create something called an optimizer us
The first thing we'll do is we'll get rid of
The linear one function
But remember the linear one function
Does X at W plus B
There's actually a class imply torch that does that equation for us so we may as well use it
It's called n n dot linear and n n dot linear does two things it does
that
Function for us and it also initializes the parameters for us so we don't have to do
weights and bias in it params
anymore
We just create an N n dot linear class and that's going to create a matrix of size
28 by 28 comma 1 and a bias of size 1
It will set requires grade equals true for us. It's all going to be encapsulated in this class
And then when I call that as a function
it's going to do my
X at W plus B
So to see the parameters in it, we would expect it to contain
784 weights in one bias, we can just call that parameters and we can D structure it to W comma B and C
Yep, it is
784 and
One for the weights and bias
So that's cool. So this is just
You could you know, it could be an interesting exercises for you to create this class yourself from scratch
You should be able to at this point
So that you can confirm that you can recreate something that behaves exactly like a tenth linear
So now that we've got this object which contains our parameters in a parameters
Method we could now create an optimizer. So if you optimize that we're going to pass it the parameters to optimize and a learning rate
will store them away and
We'll have something called step which goes through each parameter and does that thing?
we just saw P type data - equals P grad x learning rate and
it's also going to have something called zero grad which goes through each parameter and
Zeroes it out, or we could even just set it to none
So that's the thing. We're going to call basic optimizer. So those is exactly the same lines of code
We've already seen wrapped up into a class so we can now create an optimizer
passing in the parameters of the linear model with ease and our learning rate and
so now our training loop is
Look through each mini batch in the data loader
Calculate the gradient
opt step
up to zero grad
That's it
Function doesn't have to change
Put our training loop into a function that's going to loop through a bunch of epochs call an epoch print validate epoch
And then run it and it's the same
we're getting a slightly different result here, but
Much much the same idea. Okay
so
That's cool, right we've now
Refactoring using you know, create our own optimizer
And using faster plate Watchers built-in in and linnea class
And you know, by the way
we don't actually need to use our own basic optim not surprisingly pate which comes with something which does exactly this and
Not surprisingly. It's called STD
So and actually this SGD is provided by fast AI first AI and pi torch provides some overlapping functionality
Then work much the same way so you can pass to SGD
Your parameters and your learning rate just like basic opt-in. Okay, and
Train it and get the same result
So as you can see these
classes that are in fast, I am pay torch and not
mysterious they're just
Pretty you know in wrappers around
Functionality that we've now written ourself. So there's quite a few steps there
And if you haven't done gradient descent before then, there's a lot of unpacking
so so this this lesson
Is kind of the key lesson it's the one where you know like we should you know
Really take us stop and a deep breath at this point and make sure you're comfortable. What's the data set?
What's the data loader?
What's in n dot Linea?
What's SGD and if you you know if want any any or all of those don't make sense go back to where we defined it
from scratch using
Python code well the data loader we didn't define from scratch, but it you know, the functionality is not particularly
Interesting, you can certainly create your own from scratch if you wanted to that would be another pretty good exercise
Let's refactor some more
Buster has a data loaders class which is as we've mentioned before is a tiny class
That just you pass it a bunch of data loaders and it just stores them away as a dot train and a dot valid
Even though it's a tiny class. It's it's super handy because with that we now have a
single object that knows all the data we have and so it can make sure that your
Training data loader is shuffle and your validation loader isn't shuffled, you know, make sure everything works properly
so that's what the data loaders class is you can pass in the training and valid data loader and
then the next thing we have in fast AI is the learner class and
the learner class is something where we're going to pass in our
data loaders, we're going to pass in our
Model we're going to pass in
Our optimization function we're going to pass in our loss function. We're going to pass in our metrics
So all the stuff we've just done manually
That's all learner does is it's just going to do that for us?
So it's just going to call this train model and this train epoch
It's just you know, it's inside learner. So now if we go
my own dot fit
You can see again. It's doing the same thing getting the same result
And it's got some nice functionality
It's printing it out into a pretty table for us and it's showing us the losses and the accuracy and how long it takes
But there's nothing magic right you've been able to do exactly the same thing
by hand using
Python and PI torch, okay
So these abstractions are here to like let you write less code and to save some time and to save some
Cognitive overhead, but they're not doing anything. You can't do yourself
And that's important right because if the if if if they're doing things you can't do yourself
Then you can't
Customize them you can't debug with them. You know, you can't profile them
so we want to make sure that the the
The stuff we're using is stuff that we understand what it's doing
So this is just a linear function is not great we want a neural network
So, how do we turn this?
into a neural network or
remember
This is a linear function X set W plus B to turn it into a neural network
We have two linear functions
Exactly the same but with different weights and different biases and in between
This magic line of code
Which takes the result of our first linear function and then does a max between that and zero
So a max of res and a zero is going to take any negative numbers and turn them into zeros
So we're going to do a linear function
We're going to replace the negatives with zero and then we're going to take that and put it through another linear function that
Believe it or not is a neuro net
so
W1 and w2 were weight tensors b1 and b2 abayas tensors just like before so we can initialize them
Just like before and we could now call exactly the same training code that we did before to
roll these
So res dot max zero
Linear unit, but you will always see referred to as
value and
So here is and and in pi torch it already has
This function it's called f dot value. And so if we plot it you can see it's as you'd expect
It's zero or negative numbers and then it's y equals x for positive numbers
So
You know, here's some jargon
Rectified linear units sounds scary sounds complicated, but it's actually this incredibly tiny
line of code this incredibly simple function and this happens a lot in
deep learning things that sound complicated and sophisticated and impressive turnout to be
Normally super simple frankly at least once, you know what it is
so
Why do we do?
Linear layer really many Alea. Well if we got rid of the middle
If we got rid of the middle
Value and just went linear layer linear layer
then you could rewrite that as a single linear layer when your model playthings an ad and then multiply things and add and
You can just change the coefficients and make it into a single multiply and then add
So no matter how many linear layers we stack on top of each other we can never make anything more
And of effective than a simple linear model
But if you put a non-linearity between the linear layers
Then actually you have the opposite. This is now aware
Something called the universal approximation theorem holds which is that if the size of the weight and bias matrices are big enough
This can actually approximate any
arbitrary function
including the function of how do I recognize threes from sevens or
Or whatever
So that's kind of amazing, right this tiny thing is actually a universal function approximator
as long as you have W 1 B 1 W 2 and B 2
Have the right numbers and we know how to make them the right numbers use SGD
Could take a very long time. It could take a lot of memory
But the basic idea is that there is some solution to any computable problem and
This is one of the biggest challenges
A lot of beginners have to deep learning is that there's nothing else to it like that? There's often this like
Okay, how do I make a neural net?
Oh, that is the neural net. Well, how do I?
Learning training with SGD
there's things to like
Make a train a bit faster. There's you know things to mean you need a few less parameters
but everything from here is
just
Performance tweaks
honestly, right
So this is you know, this is the key
understanding of of training a neural network
Okay, we can simplify things a bit more
We already know that we can use n n linear to replace
Their weight and bias, so let's do that
for both of the linear layers, and then since we're simply taking
The result of one function and passing it into the next
The result of that function passive to the next and so forth and then returned the end
this is called function composition function composition is when you just
Take the result of one function pass it to a new one take a result of one function. Pass it to a new one
and so every pretty much neural network is just doing function composition of
linear layers and
These are called activation functions or nonlinearities
So hi torch provides something to do function composition for us
And it's called n n dot sequential so it's gonna do a linear layer
Ask the result to a rel you pass the result to a linear layer
You'll see here. I'm not using F value. I'm using n n value
This is identical returns exactly the same thing, but this is a class
Rather than a function. Yes, Rachel
By using the non-linearity
Won't using a function that makes all negative output zero make many of the gradients in the network zero and stop the learning process due
to many zero gradients
Well, that's a fantastic question and the answer is yes, it does
But they won't be zero for every image and
remember the mini-batches a shuffled so
Even if it's zero for every image in one mini batch, it won't be for the next mini batch
And it won't be the next time around we go for another epoch. So
Yes, it can create zeros and if
The neural net ends up with a set of parameters
That's that lots and lots of inputs end up as zeros. You can end up with whole mini batches that are zero and
You can end up in a situation where some of the neurons
In active inactive means their zero and they're basically dead units
And this is a huge problem
It basically means you're wasting computation
So there's a few tricks to avoid that which we'll be learning about a lot one. Simple trick is to
Not make this thing flat here, but just make it a less steep
Mine that's called a leaky. Well, you leaky rectified linear unit and
It that they helped a bit
As well learn though even better is to make sure that we just kind of initialize two
sensible initial values that are not too big and not too small and step by sensible announce that are
particularly not too big and generally if we do that we can keep things in the zone where they're
positive most of the time but we are going to learn about
how to actually analyze inside a network and find out how many dead units we have how many of these zeros we have because
As is as you point out they are they are bad news. They don't do any work
Continue to not do any work if enough of the inputs end up being zero
Okay, so now that we've got a neural net
We can use exactly the same learner we had before but this time we pass in the simple net
Instead of the linear one. Everything else is assumed and
we can call fit just like before and
Generally as your models get deeper. So here we've gone from one layer. Ooh
And I'm only counting the parameterised layers as layers. You could say it's three. I was going to call it two. There's two
Trainable layers. So I've gone from one layer to I've checked dropped my learning rate from 1 to 0.1
because the deeper models
It all tend to be kind of bumpier less nicely behaved so often you need to use lower learning rates
And so we trained it for a while
okay, and
Can actually find out what that training looks like by looking inside our learner and there's an attribute we create for your chord recorder and
That's going to record
Well everything that appears in this table
Basically, well these three things the training loss the validation loss and the accuracy or any metrics
so recorded values
contains that kind of table of results and so item number two of
Each row will be the accuracy
and so the
capital L class, which I'm using here as a
nice little method chord item got that will will get
The second item from every row and then I can plot that
How the training went and I can get the final accuracy
By grabbing the last row of the table and grabbing the second
It's indexed to 0 1 2 then my final accuracy. Not bad
98.3%
So this is pretty amazing, we now have a function that can solve any problem
To any level of accuracy if we can find the right parameters and we have a way to find
Hopefully the best or at least a very good that our parameters for any function
So this is kind of the magic yes, Rachel
How could we use what we're learning here to get an idea of what the network is learning along the way
Like Sylar and Fergus did more or less
We will look at that later
Not in the full detail of their paper
but basically
You can look in the dot parameters to see the values of those parameters
and
At this point. Well, I mean, why don't you try it yourself? Right? You've actually got now
The parameters, so if you want to grab the model you can actually see learned up model
So we can we can look inside learned up model to see the actual model that we just trained and
You can see it's got the three things in it. They're linear that rather than linear
And you know, what I kind of like to do is to put that into a variable
Bit easy to work with
Can grab one Leia by indexing in
Parameters
And
That just gives me a something called a generator
It's something that will give me a list of the parameters when I ask for them. I could just go white comma bias equals
2d structure them and so the weight
Here's
birdie by 784
Because that's what I asked for. So one of the things to note here is
that
to create a
Neural net so something that's more than one layer. I
Actually have thirty outputs not just one right so I'm kind of generating lot
So if you can think of as generating lots of features
So it's kind of like 30 different linear of linear models here and then I combined those 30 back into one
So you could look at
one of those by having a look at
Yeah, so there's first bro, we could reshape that
Into the the original shape of the images and we could even have a look
And there it is right so you can see this is something Sothis cool right we can actually see here we've got something which is
Which is kind of learning to find things at the top and the bottom and the middle
And so we could look at the second one
Okay, no idea what that's showing
And so some of them are kind of you know, I probably got far more than I need which is why they're not that obvious
But you can see yeah, here's another thing that's looking pretty similar
Kind of looking for this little bit in the middle
So yeah, this is the basic idea
To understand the features that are not the first layer but later layers, you have to be a bit more sophisticated
But yet I see the first layer ones you can you can just plot them
Okay, so then, you know just to compare we could
Use the full faster a toolkit
So grab our data loaders by using data loaders from folder as we've done before and create a CNN learner and a res net
and fit it for a single epoch and
Roll 99.7. All right, so we did 40 epochs and got
98.3 as I said using all the tricks you can
Really speed things up and make things a lot better and so by the end of this course
Or at least both parts of this course, you'll be able to from scratch at this 99.7 in a single
epoch
Um, all right, so
Jargon
So Jagan just remind us value function that returns zero for negatives
mini-batch a few inputs and labels, which optionally are
randomly selected
The forward pass is the bit where we calculate the predictions
the loss is the function that we're going to take the derivative of and
Then the gradient is the derivative of the loss with respect to each parameter
The backward pass is when we calculate those gradients
gradient descent is that full thing of taking a step in the direction opposite to the gradients by capital after calculating the loss and
Then the learning rate is the size of the step that we take
you
Other things to know
Perhaps the two most important pieces of jargon are all of the numbers that are in a neural network the
numbers that we're learning are called parameters and
Then the numbers that we're calculating so every value that's calculated every matrix multiplication element that's calculated
They're called activations
so activations and parameters are
All of the numbers in the neural net and so be very careful when I say from here on in in these lessons
activations or parameters
You've got to make sure you know what those mean because that's that's the entire basically almost the entire set of numbers that exist
Inside a neural net so activations are calculated
Parameters are learned
We're doing this stuff with tensors and tensors are just regularly shaped to raise
Rank zero tensors, we call scalars rank 1 tensors. We call vectors rank two tensors
we call matrices and we continue on to rank 3 tensors rank 4 tensors and so forth and
Rag five tensors are very common in deep learning. So don't be scared of going up to higher numbers of dimensions
Okay, so let's have a break oh we got a question, okay
Is there a rule of thumb for what non-linearity to choose given that there are many?
Yeah, there are many non Nerys to choose from and it doesn't generally matter very much which you choose so there's two Israeli
or Leakey irelia or
Yeah, whatever any anyone
Should work fine later on we'll we'll look at the minor differences between between them
But it's not so much something that you pick on a per problem
It's more like some take a little bit longer and a little bit more accurate and some over it faster and a little bit less
accurate
That's a good question, okay. So before you move on it's really important that you finish the questionnaire for this chapter because
there's a whole lot of concepts that we've just done so, you know try to go through the questionnaire go back and relook at the
Notebook and please run the code through the cat experiments and make sure it makes sense
All right. Let's have a
Seven minute break see you back here in seven minutes time
1:09:44.980,1:09:46.980 =======================================================================================================================================
Okay, welcome back
So now that we know how to create and train an ear on it
Let's cycle back and look deeper at some applications. And so we're going to try to kind of
Interpolate in from one end we've done they're kind of from scratch version at the other end
We've done the kind of four lines of code version and we're going to gradually nibble at each end
Until we find ourselves in the middle and we've we've we've touched on all of it
so let's go back up to the kind of the four lines of code version and and
Delve a little deeper
So
Let's go back to pets
And let's think though about like
How do you actually?
it'll start with a new data set and
Figure out how to use it
So it you know
The the data sets we provide it's easy enough to untie them you to say untie that or download it and hire it
If it's a data set that you're getting you can just use the terminal or I
Throw a Python or whatever
um
So let's assume we have a path that's pointing at something so initially you don't you don't know what that something is
So we can start by doing LS to have a look and see what's inside there
So the pets data set that we saw in Lesson one
contains three things annotations images and models and
You'll see we have this little trick here
where we say path based path equals and
Then the path to our data and that just does a little simple thing. Where when we print it out
It just doesn't show us. It just shows us relative to this path, which is a bit convenient
So
Go and have a look at the readme for the original pets data set
It tells you what these images and annotations folders are and not surprisingly the images path
So if we go path slash images, that's how we use path Lib to grab her sub directory and then LS
We can see here are the names that the paths through the images?
As it mentions here most functions and methods in Farsi I which returned a collection don't return a
Python list that they returned a capital L and a capital L
As we briefly mentioned is basically an enhanced list. One of the enhancements is the way it prints the
Representation of it starts by showing you. How many items there are in the list in the collection?
so there's seven thousand three hundred and ninety four images and
It it if there's more than ten things it truncates it and just says dot dot to avoid filling up your screen
So there's a couple of little conveniences there
And so we can see from this output that a file name
as we mentioned in
lesson 1 if the first letter is a capital it means it's a cat and
If the first letter is lowercase
It means it's a dog
But this time we've got to do something a bit more complex a lot more complex
Which is figure out what breed it is and so you can see the breed
Is kind of everything up to after the in the file name?
It's everything up to the the last underscore and before this number is the breed
so
We want to label everything with its breed, so we're going to take advantage of this structure
So
Their way I would do this is to use a regular expression a regular expression is something that looks at a string and
Basically lets you kind of pull it apart into its pieces in very flexible way. It is kind of simple little
Language for doing that. Um, if you haven't used regular expressions before um,
Please Google regular expression tutorial now and look it's going to be like one of the most useful tools
You'll come across in your life. I use them almost every day
I
Will go to details about how to use them since there's so many great tutorials. And there's also a lot of great like
Exercises, you know, there's regex regex is short for regular expression. There's regex crosswords. There's rich xqa is
All kinds of core regex things a lot of people like me love this tool
in order to
There's also a regex lesson in the fast AI and LP course, maybe even to regex lessons. Oh, yeah
I'm sorry for forgetting about the first day. I know because
What an excellent resource that is?
So
Regular expressions are how to get right the first time. So the best thing to do is to get a sample string
So good - good way to do that would be to just grab one of the file names. So let's pop it in F name
and then you can experiment with
Vector expressions. So re is the regular expression module in Python and
Find all we'll just grab
All the parts of a regular expression that have parentheses around them
So this regular expression and R is a special kind of string in Python
Which basically says don't treat backslash is special because normally in Python like backslash n means a newline
So here's us a string
Which I'm going to capture
Any letter
one or more times
followed by an underscore
followed by a digit one or more times
Followed by anything I published have use backslash dot for this phone followed by the letters jpg followed by the end of the string
and so if I call that vector expression against my bio names name Oh
Looks good, right so we kind of check it out
So now that seems to work we can create a data block
where the
Independent variables are images the dependent variables are categories just like before get items is going to be get image files
We're going to spit it randomly as per usual
And then we're going to get the label by calling regex labeler, which is a
Just a handy little
faster class which labels things with a regular expression
We can't call the regular expression this particular regular expression directly on the path lib path object
we actually want to call it on the name attribute and
fast AI has a nice little function chord using Etra using attribute which takes this function and
Changes it to a function which will be passed this attribute that's going to be using regex labeler on the name attribute
And then from that data block we can create the data loaders as usual
There's two interesting lines here
resize
and/or transforms log transforms we have seen before in notebook 2
In the section core data augmentation
and so ork transforms was the thing which
can zoom in and zoom out and warp and rotate and change contrast and change brightness and so forth and flip
To kind of give us almost. It's like giving us more data being generated synthetically from the data. We already have
And we also learned about random resize crop
Which is a kind of a really cool way of
getting
ensuring you get square images at the same time that you're
augmenting the data
Here
We have a resize to a really large image
but you know by deep learning standards for 60 by for 60 is a really large image and
Then we're using
Oak transforms with a size. So that's actually going to use random resize crop to a smaller size
Why are we doing that?
This particular combination of two steps does something which I think is unique to fast AI which we call pre sizing and
The best way is I will show you this beautiful
Example of
Wizardry that I'm so excited about
to show how pre sizing works
What pre sizing does is that first step where we say resize to 460 by 460 is it grabs a square?
And it grabs it randomly if it's a kind of landscape orientation photo, it'll grab it randomly
So it'll take the whole height and randomly grab somewhere from along the side
If it's a portrait orientation, then it or grab it
You know take the full wits and grab a grant and grab a random bit from top to bottom
So then we take this area here and here
It is right
And so that's what the first resize does and then the second org transforms bit will grab a random
wat
crop
Be rotated from in here and we'll turn that into a square and
so it does
So there's two steps its first of all resize to a square. That's big and
then the second step is to a kind of rotation and warping and
zooming stage to something smaller
in this case 224 by 224
Because his first step creates something that's Square
And always is the same size the second step can happen on the GPU and because normally things like rotating an image whopping
Actually pretty slow
Also normally doing a zoom and rotate and a warp
Actually is really destructive to the image because each one of those things requires an interpolation step
Which it's not just slow it actually makes the image really
quite low quality
So we do it in a very special way in faster. I think it's unique
Where we do all of the all of these kind of coordinate transforms like rotations and warps and zooms and so forth
Not on the actual pixels, but instead we kind of keep track of the
Changing coordinate values in a in a non lossy way so the full floating-point value and then once at the very end
We then do the interpolation
There is also quite striking
Here is what the difference looks like
Hopefully you can see this on on the video
on the left is our pre sizing approach and
On the right is the standard approach that other libraries use and you can see that the one on the right is a lot less
Nicely focused and it also has like weird things like this should be grass here
But it's actually got its kind of bum sticking way out
This has a little bit of weird distortions. This has got loads of weird distortions
So you can see the pre sized version really ends up. I'm way way better and
I think we have a question Rachel
Are the blocks in the data block an ordered list
They specify the input and output structures respectively. Are there always two blocks or can there be more than two?
For example, if you wanted a segmentation model with the second block be something about segmentation
So so, yeah, this is an ordered list
So the first item says I want to create an image
And then the second item says I want to create a category. So that's my independent and dependent variable
You can't have one thing here. You can have three things here. You can have any amount of things here you want
Obviously the vast majority of the time it'll be two only there's an independent variable and a dependent variable
We'll be seeing this in more detail later
Although if you go back to the earlier lesson when we introduced data blocks, I do have a picture kind of showing how these pieces
Get together
So after you've put together datablock created your data loaders you want to make sure it's working correctly
so the obvious thing to do for a computer vision data block is show batch and
Show batch will show you
The items and you can kind of just make sure they look
Sensible that looks like the labels are reasonable
If you add a unique equals true, then it's going to show you the same image with all the different augmentations
This is a good way to make sure your augmentations work
If you make a mistake in your data block in this example, there's no
resize so that different
Images are going to be different sizes or be impossible to collate them
Into a batch, so if you call dot summary
This is a really neat thing
Which we'll go through and tell you everything that's happening though. I collecting the items. How many did I find?
What happened when I split them?
What are the different?
Variables independent independent variables on creating let's try and create one of these
peers each step
Create my image
Categorize is what the first thing gave me an American Bulldog
is the final sample is this image this size this category and
Then eventually it says oh, oh it's not possible to collect your items. I tried to collect the zero index members of your tuples
So in other words, that's the independent variable and I got this was size 500 by 375. This was 375 by 500
Oh, I can't collate these into a tensor because they're different sizes
So this is a super great debugging tool for debugging your data blocks ever question
How does the item transforms
Precise work if the resize is smaller than the image is
A whole width or height still taken or is it just a random crop with the revised value?
so if you remember back to
To
We looked at the different ways of
Creating these things you can use squish
Can use pad
Or you can use crop
so if your image is smaller than the precise value then
Squish will really be zoom so it will just small stretch. It'll stretch it and then
Pattern crop will do much the same thing. And so you'll just end up with a you're not the same
This looks like these but it'll be a kind of lower more pixelated lower resolution because it's having to zoom in a little bit
Okay, so a lot of people say that you should do a hell of a lot of data cleaning before you model
We don't we say model as soon as you can
because
Remember what we found in in notebook - your your model can teach you about the problems in?
your data
so as soon as I've got to a point where I have a data block
That's working and I have data loaders. I'm going to build a model
And so here I'm you know, it also tells me how I'm going. So I'm getting 7% era. Wow, that's actually really good or
A pets model and so at this point now that I have a model I can do that stuff
We learned about earlier in our to the notebook or to where we trained our model and use it to clean the data
So we can look at the classification a confusion matrix
top losses
The image cleaner widget, you know so forth
Okay, now one thing interesting here is in book 4 we
Included a loss function when we created a loner and here we don't pass in our loss function
Why is that and that's because plus say I will try to
Automatically pick a somewhat sensible loss function for you
And so for a image classification task it knows what loss function is the normal one to pick and it's done it for you
but let's have a look and see what actually
did pick
So we could have a look
At learned loss funk and we will see it is cross-entropy loss
Why don't know this' cross-entropy loss i'm glad you asked let's find out
Cross entropy loss is really much the same as the
Amnesty lost we created with that with that sigmoid and the one minus
predictions and predictions
But it's it's a kind of extended version of that
now and the extended version of that is that
that torch dot where that we looked at in notebook for only works when you have um a
Binary outcome in that case it was is it a three or not?
but in this case we've got
Which of the thirty-seven pet breeds is it?
So we want to kind of create
something just like that sigmoid and torch don't wear that which also works nicely for
more than two
categories
So, let's see how we can do that, so first of all, let's grab a batch yes a question
Why do we want to build a model before cleaning the data I would think a clean dataset would help in training
Yeah, absolutely a current clean dataset helps in training but remember as we saw in notebook o2
An initial model helps you clean the data set. So remember how plot top losses helped us identify
mislabeled images and the
confusion matrix helps us recognize
which things we were getting confused and might need you know fixing and
the image classifier cleaner actually
Let us find things like an image that contain two bears rather than one bear and clean it up
so a model is just a fantastic way to
Help you zoom in on the data that matters which things into have the problems which things are most important
Stuff like that so you would go through and you clean it
With the model helping you and then you go back and train it again with the clean data
Thanks. Let go question
Okay, so
In order to understand cross-entropy loss. Let's grab a batch of data which we can use deals one batch
And that's going to grab a batch from the training set we could also go first DL strain
And that's going to do exactly the same thing
And so then we destructor that into the independent independent variable and so the dependent variable
Shows us we've got a batch size of 64. So it shows us the 64
categories
And
Remember those numbers simply refer to the index of into the vocab. So for example 16
Is a boxer and
So that all happens for you automatically when we say show batch it shows us those strings
So is a first mini batch
So now we can view the predictions that is the activations of the final layer of the network
by calling get prints and
You can pass in a data loader
And a DOTA loader can really be anything that's going to return
A sequence of mini batches so we can just pass in a list containing our mini batch as a data loader
And so that's going to get the predictions for one mini batch
So here's some predictions
Okay, so the actual predictions if we go
Preds zero-sum to grab the predictions for the first image and add them all up. They add up to one and
there are
37 of them so that makes sense. Right? It's like the very first thing is what is the probability that that is a
Else. Oh cab
The first thing is what's the probability it's an Abyssinian cat
It's ten to the negative six
You see and so forth
So it's basically like it's not this it's not this it's not this and you can look through and oh here this one here
You know don't see what other things it is
So
How did it?
you know, so we we obviously want the probabilities to sum to one because it would be pretty weird if
if they didn't it would say
You know that the the probability of being one of these things is more than 1 or less than 1 which would be extremely odd
So
How do we go about creating these?
Predictions where each one is between zero and one and they all add up to 1
To do that we use something called softmax
Softmax is basically an extension of sigmoid the handle more than
Two levels two categories. So remember the sigmoid function looked like this
Use that for our 3s vs. 7s model
So what if we want
Categories rather than two categories. We need one activation for every category
So actually
the threes and sevens model
Rather than thinking of that as an is-3
Model we could actually say oh that has two categories
so let's actually create two activations one representing how three like something is and one representing how seven like something is
so let's say you know, let's just
Say that we have
6m nest digits and
These were the
Can I do this and this first column were the activations of
My model
for for one
Activation and the second column was for a second activation
So my final layer actually has two activations now. So this is like how much like a3 is it?
And this is how much like a7 is it? But this one is not at all
Like a3 and it's slightly not like a seven
this is
Very much like a three and not much like a seven and so forth
So we can take that model and rather having rather than having one
Activation food-like is three we can have two activations for how much like a three how much like a seven?
So if we take the sigmoid of that
We get two numbers between Norton one
But they don't add up
To one so that doesn't make any sense. It can't be 0.66 chance. It's a three and point five six chance
It's a seven because every digit in that data set is only one or the other
So that's not going to work
but what we could do is we could take the difference between this value and this value and
Say that's how likely it is to be a three
So in other words this one here with a high number here and a low number here is very likely to be a three
So we could basically say in the binary case
These activations that what really matters is their relative confidence of being a three versus a seven
So we could create collect the difference between column one and column two and column index zero and column index one, right? And here's the
Difference between the two columns. There's that big difference and we could take the sigmoid of that
Okay, and
so this is now giving us a
single number between Norton one and
So then since we wanted two columns
We could make
column index zero the sigmoid and column index one could be one minus that and now look these all
Add up to one
So here's probability of three probability of seven, but the second one probably three properly seven and so forth
So like that's a way that we could go from
Having
Activations for every image
- creating two probabilities each of which is between Norton one and each pair of which adds to one
Great how do we extend that to more than two columns?
how to extend it to more than two columns we use this function
Which is called soft max
Those soft max is equal to e to the X
By some of a to the X
Just to show you if I go softmax on my activations I get
0.6 o2 five point three nine seventy five
Point six zero two five point three nine seven five I get exactly the same thing
Right. So softmax in the binary case is
identical to
The sigmoid that we just looked at
But in the multi category case
We basically end up with something like this. Let's say we were doing the teddy bear grizzly bear brown bear and
For that remember our neural net is going to have the final layer will have three activations. So let's say it was 0.02
negative 2.49
1.25. So to calculate softmax. I first go e to the power of
each of these three things
so here's E to the power of point O two e
to the power of negative two point four nine e
To the power of three point 4 e to the power of one point two five
Ok, then I add them up
so there's the sum of the X and then softmax will simply be one point O two divided by four point six and
Then this one will be 0.08 divided by four point six. And this one will be three point four nine divided by four point six
So since each one of these represents each number divided by the sum, that means that the total is one
okay, and
Because all of these are positive and each one is an item divided by the sum
It means all of these must be between naught and one
So this shows you that
softmax
Always gives you numbers between naught and 1 and they always add up to 1
That in practice you can just call torch dot softmax
We'll give you this result of this
dysfunction
So you should experiment with
This in your own time, you know write this out by hand and try putting in
these numbers
Right and and see how that you get back the numbers
I claim you're going to get back and make sure this makes sense to you
so one of the interesting points about softmax is
Remember I told you that X is e to the power of something and
Now what that means? Is that e to the power of something
Grows, very very fast. Right? So like
Exper for
Is 54
XP of eight
Is 29 2009 80 right it grows super fast and
What that means is that if you have one activation, it's just a bit bigger than the others
It's softmax will be a lot bigger than the others
So intuitively the softmax function
Really wants to pick one class
among the others
Which is generally what you want right when you're trying to train a classifier
To say which breed is it you kind of want it to to pick one and kind of go for it, right?
And so that's what softmax
does
That's not what you always want
So sometimes an inference time you want it to be a bit cautious
And so you kind of got to remember that softmax isn't always the perfect approach
But it's the default. It's what we use most of the time and it works well on a lot of situations
So that is
softmax
now in the binary case for the amnesty three versus sevens
This was how we calculated amnesty law suite oook the sigmoid and then we did either one minus that or that as our loss function
Um just fine as you saw it it worked, right?
Could do this
Exactly the same thing. We can't use torch dot wear anymore because targets aren't just zero or one targets could be any number from naught
to 36
So we could do that by
replacing the torch dot wear with
Indexing. So here's an example for the binary case. Let's say these are our targets
0 1 0 1 1 0 and
These are our softmax activation x' which we calculated before notice from some random numbers just for a toy example
So one way to do instead of doing torch dot where
We could instead
Have a look at this
I could say I could grab all the numbers from naught to 5 and if I index into here
With all the numbers from 0 to 5 and then my targets
0 1 0 1 0 1 1 0 then what that's going to do is it's going to pick a
row 0 it'll pick
0.6. And then for Row 1
It'll pick one
0.49 a row 2. It'll pick 0
point 1 3 0 4
It'll pick
1.00 3 and so forth. So this is a super nifty
indexing expression
which
You should definitely play with right and it's basically this trick of passing multiple things to the PI torch
Indexer, the first thing says which rows should you return and the second thing says for each of those rows?
Which column should you return? So this is returning all the rows and
These columns for each one and so this is actually identical
Don't wear
Or isn't that tricky? And so the nice thing is we can now use that for more than just two values
And so here's here's the fully worked out thing, so I've got my three is column I've got my sevens column
Here's that target is the indexes from naught one, two, three, four five. And so here's zero zero point six one one
five point nine zero two point
one three and so forth
So yeah this works just as well with more than two columns
So we can add
You know for doing a full amnesty, you know, so all the digits from naught to nine
We could have ten columns and we would just be indexing into the ten
So this thing we're doing where we're going -
our activations matrix
all of the numbers from naught to N and then our targets
Is exactly the same as something that already exists in PI torch called F dot ll us as you can see
Exactly the same at so again, we're kind of seeing that these things inside PI torch and fast AI
Are just little shortcuts for stuff we can write ourselves
And ll los
Stands for negative log likelihood again, it sounds complex, but actually it's just this indexing expression
Rather confusingly, there's no log in it. We'll see why in a moment
So let's talk about logs
So
This locks this loss function
works quite well as we as we saw in the notebook o4
It's basically this it is exactly the same as we learn no Paco for just a different way of expressing it
But we can actually make it better
because remember the probabilities we're looking at are between
Norton one so they can't be smaller than zero. They can't be greater than one
Which means that if our model is trying to decide whether to protect point nine nine zero point nine nine nine
It's going to think that those numbers are very very close together, but won't really care
But actually if you think about the error
You know if there's like a hundred thing a thousand things
Then this would like be ten things are wrong
And this would be like one thing is wrong. But this is really like ten times better than this
so
Really? What we'd like to do is to transform the numbers between zero and one two instead but three be between negative infinity and infinity
and
There's a function that does exactly that which is called
logarithm
Okay, so as the so the numbers we could have can be between zero and one
and as we get closer and closer to
Zero
It goes down to infinity and then at one
It's going to be zero and we can't go
above zero because
Our loss function we want to be negative
So
This logarithm in case you forgot hopefully use vaguely
Remember what logarithm is from high school?
but that basically the definition is is is this if you have some number that is why that is B to the power of a
Then logarithm is defined such that
a
Equals the logarithm of Y comma B in other words it tells you
B to the power of what equals y
Which is
Not that interesting of itself but one of the really interesting things about logarithms is this
Very cool relationship, which is that log of a times B
Equals log of a plus log of B
And we use that all the time in deep learning and machine learning
because
This number here a times B can get very very big or very very small if you multiply things
a lot of small things together
You'll get a tiny number if you multiply a lot of big things together
You'll get a huge number it can get so big or so small that the the kind of the precision in your computer's floating-point
Gets really bad
Where else this thing here adding is not going to get out of control. So we really love using logarithms
Like particularly in a deep neural net where there's lots of layers
We're kind of multiplying and adding many times though. This kind of tends to come out quite nicely
So
When we take thee
The probabilities that we saw before the
Deck the things that came out of this function
And retake their logs
And we take the main that is called negative log-likelihood
And so this ends up being kind of a really nicely behaved number because of this property of the log that we described
So if you take the softmax and then take the log
Then pass that to an ll loss because remember that didn't actually take the log at all despite the name that gives you
Russ entropy loss
So that leaves an obvious question of
Why?
doesn't nll loss actually take the log and
The reason for that is that it's more convenient
Computationally to actually take the log back at the softmax step. So pi torch has a function called
Softmax
So since it's actually easier to do the log at the softmax stage
It's just a faster and more accurate pay torch assumes that you use soft log max and then pass that to n ll us
So an L. Our loss does not do the log. It assumes that you've done the log beforehand
So log softmax followed by n ll loss is the definition of cross-entropy loss in pay torch
So that's our loss function and so you can pass that some activations and some targets and get back a number and
Pretty much everything in in pi torch every every one of these kinds of functions
You can either use the NN version as a class like this and then call that object as if it's a function
Or you can just use F dot
With the camelcase name as a function directly and as you can see, they're exactly the same number
People normally use the class version
In the documentation in pi torch, you'll see it normally uses a class version so will tend to use the class version as well
You'll see that it's returning a single number and
that's because it takes the mean because a loss needs to be as we've discussed the main but if you want to see the underlying
numbers before taking the mean you can just pass in reduction equals none and
That shows you the individual cross-entropy losses before
taking the mean
Okay
Great so this is a good place to stop with our
Discussion of
Loss functions and such things rich or were there any questions about this?
Why does the loss function need to be negative
Well, okay, I mean I guess it doesn't but it's
We want something that that the lower it is the better
And we kind of need it to cut off
somewhere
I have to think about this more more during the week because I'm it's a bit tough a bit tired
Yeah, so let me let me refresh my memory when I'm awake
Okay now
Next week
Well, nope not for the video next week actually happened last week so it's the thing I'm about to say is actually your
So next week we're going to be talking about
data ethics, and I wanted to kind of segue into that by talking about
My weeks gone
because
a week or two ago in a did a
as part of a lesson I
actually talked about the efficacy of
Masks, I mean specifically wearing masks in public and I pointed out that
The efficacy of masks seemed like it could be really high and maybe everybody should be wearing them
And
Somehow I
myself as the face of a global advocacy campaign
and so if you go to masks or
Osseo
Ah you will find
Website
um
Talking about
masks and I've been on
you know TV shows in South Africa and the US and England and Australia and on radio and
blah blah blah talking about
masks
Why is this? Well, it's because as
a data scientist
you know, I
noticed that the data around masks
Seem to be getting misunderstood and it seemed that that misunderstanding was costing possibly
hundreds of thousands of lives
you know literally in the places that were using masks it seemed to be associated with you know orders of magnitude fewer deaths and
To talk about next week is like, you know, what's your role is a data scientist and and you know
I strongly believe that it's to understand the data and then do something about it and
So nobody was talking about this
so I
Ended up writing an article that appeared in The Washington Post
That basically called on people to really consider
Asks which is this article and
You know, I was I was I managed to kind of get a huge team of brilliant
Not I'm not huge a pretty decent-sized team of brilliant volunteers who helped?
You know kind of build this website and kind of some PR folks and stuff like that
But what these came clear was?
and I was talking to politicians, you know, and it is laughs is what was becoming clear is that
people weren't convinced by the science, which is fair enough because it's it's hard to
you know when the whro and the CDC is saying
You don't need to wear a mask and some random data scientist is saying but doesn't seem to be what the data is showing
You know, you've got half a brain you would pick the whu-oh in the CDC not the random data scientist
So I really felt like I if I was going to be an effective advocate I needed
sort the science out and it
You know credentialism is strong
And so it wouldn't be enough for me to say it. I needed to find other people to say it
so I put together a team of
scientists
Including you know a professor of sociology
a professor of aerosol dynamics
The founder of an African movement that's that kind of studied preventive methods for methods for tuberculosis
a Stanford professor who studies
Mask
disposal and cleaning methods
see a bunch of Chinese scientists who study
epidemiology modeling
a UCLA professor
who is
one of the top
Infectious disease epidemiologist experts
and so forth so like this kind of all-star team of people from all around the world and
I had never met any of these people before so well, I don't know not quite sure
I knew Austin a little bit and I knew they nip a little bit
And helix a little bit
But on the whole you know, and well Reshma, we all know she's awesome
So it's great to actually have a pastor a community person there too. And
So but yeah, I kind of tried to pull together
people from you know, there's many geographies as possible and as many areas of expertise as possible and
You know the kind of the global community helped me find
Papers about about everything about you know how different materials work about how droplets form about
Epidemiology about
Case studies of
people infecting with and without masks blah blah blah and
We ended up in the last week. Basically we wrote this paper
It contains 84
citations
um and
You know, we basically worked around the clock on it as a team and
It's out and it's been sent to a number of some of the earlier versions three or four days ago we sent to some
Governments, so one of the things is in this team. I try to look for people who
Well what you know working closely with government leaders, not just that they're scientists. And so this this went out to a number of
government ministers and
in the last few days, I've heard that it was a
very significant part of
decisions by governments to change their
To change their guidelines around masks
And you know the fights not over by any means and in particular the UK is a bit of a holdout
But I'm going to be on
ITV tomorrow and then BBC the next day
You know, it's it's kind of required stepping out to be a lot more than just a data scientist so I've had to
Pull together, you know
Politicians and staffers I've had to you know
You know hassle with the media to try and get you know coverage and you know today I'm now
Starting to do a lot of work with unions to try to get unions to understand this, you know
It's really a case of like saying okay as a data scientist
and income in conjunction with
real scientists
We've built this really strong understanding that
Masks, you know this simple, but incredibly powerful tool
That doesn't do anything unless I can effectively communicate this to
Decision-makers. So today I was you know on the phone to
You know one of the top union leaders in the country
Explaining what this means basically it turns out that in buses
In America, the kind of the air conditioning is set up so that it blows from the back to the front
and there's actually case studies in the medical literature of how
People that are seated and of downwind of an air conditioning unit
In a restaurant ended up all getting sick with Co at 19 and so we can see why like bus drivers are dying
Because they're like, they're right in the wrong spot here and their passengers aren't wearing masks so I could have unexplained this science
To union leaders
So that they understand that to keep the workers safe
It's not enough just for the driver to wear a mask. But all the people on the bus needed to be wearing masks as well
so, you know all this is basically to say
You know as data scientists, I think we have a responsibility to
The study the data and then do something about it, it's not just a
Research, you know exercise it's not just a computation exercise
You know, what? What's the point of doing things if it doesn't lead to anything?
So
Um, yeah, so
Next week. We'll be talking about this a lot more but I think you know
this is a really to me kind of interesting example of how
Digging into the data can lead to really amazing things happening. And and in this case I
strongly believe and a lot of people are telling me they strongly believe that this kind of
Advocacy work that's come out of this data analysis is is already saving lives. And so I hope this might help inspire you
To to take your data analysis and to take it to places that it really makes a difference
So thank you very much, and I'll see you next week